South African Prosecutors Start Push to Appeal Pistorius’s Sentence
Alan Cowell

LONDON — Weeks after a judge sent the track star Oscar Pistorius to prison for killing his girlfriend, prosecutors in South Africa on Tuesday began an effort to appeal the sentence, calling it “shockingly inappropriate” to the crime.
The hearing was the latest twist in a drama that began on Feb. 14, 2013, when Mr. Pistorius shot dead his girlfriend, Reeva Steenkamp, a law graduate and model, at his upscale villa in a gated complex in Pretoria, the South African capital.
The trial, which began in March, was broadcast around the world and followed by millions.
Mr. Pistorius was sentenced to jail for five years in late October, but under South African law, the decision meant he could serve just a sixth of the sentence — 10 months — before being released to house arrest.
The judge, Thokozile Matilda Masipa, acquitted him of murder charges but found him guilty of culpable homicide, which is equivalent to manslaughter. On Tuesday, the judge listened to the arguments for and against an appeal and said she would respond on Wednesday.
Ms. Steenkamp died after Mr. Pistorius shot four rounds from a handgun through a locked toilet cubicle door, but he said he did not know she was on the other side of it.
South African judicial rules meant that Judge Masipa, who conducted Mr. Pistorius’s trial and handed down the sentence, also presided over Tuesday’s hearing, at which the chief prosecutor, Gerrie Nel, sought permission to appeal to a higher court. Mr. Pistorius’s defense lawyers say they plan to oppose an appeal.
“We’re saying not enough weight was given to the consequences of what happened,” Mr. Nel said at the hearing at the high court in Pretoria, which was streamed live on South African news websites.
Mr. Pistorius argued in court during his trial that he had opened fire that night because he believed an intruder had entered his home.
“An innocent woman was shot and killed in most horrendous circumstances,” Mr. Nel said on Tuesday.
The prosecutor argued that the athlete, a double amputee since infancy who competed at both the Olympic and Paralympic Games in London in 2012, “deliberately fired four shots,” knowing that whoever was behind the door could not escape.
“It’s not someone who fired blindly,” Mr. Nel said. “Because of all the facts, we say the element of mercy was overexaggerated.”
Mr. Pistorius is serving his sentence in the hospital wing of a prison in Pretoria, and he was not present at Tuesday’s hearing, reporters in the courtroom said.
Mr. Nel argued that Mr. Pistorius should have been jailed for 10 years on the culpable homicide charge and that Judge Masipa had been too lenient. “The court imposed the shortest period of incarceration it could reasonably do,” Mr. Nel said. “What could be less than 10 months?”
He also challenged Judge Masipa’s rejection of the state’s case that Mr. Pistorius was guilty of a category of murder known as dolus eventualis since he must have known that, by firing into the toilet door, he might kill whoever was behind it, regardless of the person’s identity.
It was “inconceivable that he had any intention other than to kill that person or accepted that he may,” Mr. Nel said, effectively challenging Judge Masipa to acknowledge potential flaws in her judgment.
“The court asked the wrong question,” he said. “Those questions that should have been asked were never asked.”
Barry Roux, the lead lawyer on the Pistorius defense team, disputed Mr. Nel’s depiction of the sentence, saying that a decision to release the athlete on house arrest after 10 months was at the discretion of the courts. Even then, Mr. Roux said, the athlete would be under house arrest.
“It’s not a light sentence,” he said.
He also challenged Mr. Nel’s contention that Mr. Pistorius had committed a form of murder, saying that, in her ruling at the end of the trial in October, Judge Masipa made a “factual finding” — which could not be appealed — that Mr. Pistorius did not foresee the outcome of his actions.
The hearing on Tuesday was the second occasion in two days in which South Africa’s post-apartheid judicial system has come under scrutiny.
In another sensational trial that concluded on Monday, a British businessman, Shrien Dewani, was acquitted in Cape Town of murdering his wife, Anni Dewani, on their honeymoon in 2010. The prosecution had accused him of arranging for her to be shot dead under circumstances resembling a carjacking — a common occurrence in South Africa, which has one of the world’s highest murder rates and a reputation for gun crime.